good morning everyone and welcome back
to a whole new episode of wellness 360
at home today we've got something really
interesting for you covering well all
the essential parts of parenting so we
have with us hitier's Sharma today and
now let me tell you a little about Hatay
Sharma he is a business graduate from a
premium Business School IMT he brings in
25 years of experience in managing FMCG
consumer durables telecom and media
businesses that's a lot his experience
is not confined to one particular
industry and this has given him varied
experience of managing customers and
environments across cultures and
geographies so without further ado
here's presenting hitters Sharma founder
IDI appear live in his second session on
parenting in Covell 19 times under our
wellness 360 at home initiative Wellness
360 at home brought to you by ICICI
Lombard hi good morning everybody we are
in a crazy time and we did the first
sessions few days back on parenting in
Cobra time and now we will do the part
two life skills for our children so it's
very exciting and symbol is herself as a
parent and a blogger I am so interested
to hear all of what you have to share
today I really need it cuz I know
parenting is tough in general when
you're in covent is even harder
so hit the issue is super excited for
all the knowledge you're about to
impasse to us and all the skills you're
going to share with us okay I have a 19
year old at home so parenting is tough I
can say that and she will also tell me
tell she can tell everybody that that
her parents are not super she will
probably give us good four out of ten so
worried of you all of us are in the same
boat before we start and I'll share my
screen I'll be a short music so really
really short
from 30-second I'll play and in the
presentation also we are talking about
this album but I want to invite all the
parents who are on the on this webinar
if you've come on a Sunday morning we
would like you to just think about for
30 second of your kid and there will be
it's just to bring yourself in the
moment right now and this music will
help you I just focus on their
well-being and that's what all our
energies will be focus on
[Music]
so when I love this music and I think in
some sense it can set the mood for the
for the discussion and the presentation
I hope you can see my presentation
simple yes kattappa okay so we did the
part one they are calling it apparent
success series where we talked about
essentials of parenting and what parents
need to learn about parenting and
especially what is the impact of Cova
times on parenting I will cover in one
or two parts here is there some stuff
which we discuss in the the part one if
you are not attended you get us some
idea about that now the part two that we
are talking today after life skills for
children that what is the role of life
skills
why do we need to do it and that party
will do in next few days is about the
next decade what are the next a kid look
like and as a parents what we can do to
prepare our children for the next decade
now just come into the fact that
parenting parenting is hard and before
the start Simone and I were chatting
about it the two most essential skills
all of us end up doing a long term
relationship of a marriage
I'm the second is parenting
unfortunately in our schools in our
college these two things are not
discussed these they - things are not
talked about we are also supposed to
learn by trial and error we there are no
milestones and what stage will you call
yourself you have been a good husband or
you have been a good wife or you been a
good parent so these things are very
muddled when they confuse in our head we
all make a decent effort I think we make
sincere effort to be a good life partner
all of us make a very very sincere
effort to be a good parent and but still
these are the subjects which don't get
talked about he last few decades there's
a lot of work which has happened on on
these two areas and you want to bring
out and talk to everybody everybody
about it
now coming specifically to parents that
three things have happened because of
which some failed our generation is a
sandwich generation and what do I mean
by that if you see that three things are
there are nuclear families now there
used to be all saying that it takes a
village to raise a child and now we all
live in a small apartment small houses
because of that it's very difficult to
have an entire family supporting the
well-being of a child is one one reason
the pent parenting is the heart the
second reason is if both parents are
working if you're husband and wife both
works it becomes that much more
difficult now the third reason is if you
have a single child if you have a single
child all your attentions and all your
resources in good ways and bad ways are
diverted to to do one single child these
are there may be economic reasons or any
reason whatsoever but that makes
parenting tough so what we will do today
we will talk about what are life skills
while learning skills which are not
important how can we learn life skills
or how can we identify them and play an
active role in imparting those life
skills to our children and there are
five broad pillars of life skills that
we will talk about today
now coming to which life school do you
think is important let me talk about in
the quarry Times Spain has seen a
significant impact of Oviatt there have
been many deaths under the large steel
study which has been done recently on
the impact of Ovid on children what has
come out that it has been hugely hugely
stressful for children to suddenly deal
with an issue which is which only brings
bad news every single day we need to
understand that children even adults end
don't have mental capacity to process
information now if you pause and think
about it your age will be 3x of your
child age suppose your child is 10 years
old this probably you will be in your
forties because even if you had a child
at the age of 27 28
you will be 38 or 39 now and your child
will be 9 10 years old so there is a 3x
of your age in your in your child your
ability to process information versus
your child's ability to process
information are very different so what
do you see with this speaker study from
Spain talks about there then the
children have very difficult emotion to
process so much of negative views and
what if this study talks about is that
outdoor activities are essential for the
cognitive and emotional development of
children in whatever ways we can manage
and whatever way we can
in the sea if said setting we can bring
the outdoor activities we should do
about it and also be in this webinar
specifically talking about about life
skills which you can do it now why do we
need life skills and why do we need to
work on them unfortunately in our
society we do higher education
counseling work we see parents and
children starting from 8th 9th
onwards up to college and sometime you
and younger children than that what we
see in our society there is a super
super focus on academic performance when
we meet parents the two things we hear
almost 99.9% of time one my child is not
starting enough and the second is my
child is distracted on mobile phone so
these two are these two are almost a
pandemic in their own way that every
family seems to be affected by it
and in some sense we have an advantage
point to see how the parents from a city
like Bombay to City like Papa to jump
ship or to Jaipur suddenly seems to have
these two things which are very common
and we will talk about it now he live as
a parent we are so super focused on
academic skills that we are not looking
at that there are other areas also as a
parent we can help our children now if
you just rewind a little bit back and
look at the 20th century and 21st
century the 20th century was a one
bloody century by this 1950s there were
two world wars the a partition happened
in India we lost millions and millions
of people but after 1950s world enjoyed
a very very long period of secular rule
so almost 60 years of secular growth
followed in that process the next crisis
which happened was 2008 global financial
crisis and now in 2020 we see a fervid
crisis so what you see now put it
yourself as a parent in this time
continuum and you will see that what the
word we saw as a parent is very
different from the world our children
will see now take another
example let's say your child goes to six
standard or tenth standard let's take an
example that your child is in eighth
standard which means your child has four
more years of school left your child
goes to a bachelor degree which is less
a three year or four year let's say your
child goes to study engineering
so another four years of cheering and
let's say your child does any master
degree after that another two years of
master degree so your child will be in
some form of academic environment for
another ten years
which means we are into 2020 which child
will join the workforce in 2030 now if
you ask yourself what were you doing in
2010 did you really think very hard
because the world has changed so much in
us ten years if and this change of pace
is gonna further accelerate so what we
see this super focus of parents on
academic skills and acquiring academic
knowledge but not enabling children
towards the life skill a serious issue
in our society and we want to bring it
out and talk about it in some sense Ovid
is a is a good development and I'm
seeing in a qualified way because it
will force all of us to pause and
recalibrate our life and recalibrate and
think about it what are things we need
to impart to our our our kids now there
are two stories before we go into and I
will talk about it the picture on the
left you see this judoka in blue is it
is a Australian judoka who in London
Nolan paid in the first round got out in
24 seconds his name is Jack Andrew
gotcha he was playing in a hundred kg
category this boy young boy six feet
five inch tall weighing more than 100 kg
he stayed away from his family for six
years at the aid of
sixteen he left his home to prepare for
Olympic London Olympic at the age of 22
he participated
he was everybody was pretty sure that he
would win some medal or the other and
his life or his ambition was cut short
by in 24 seconds in 24 second he was
lost and this is a very famous picture
from London on a big when you see a Hulk
of a man on the mat grind he went on to
win more medals and do many other thing
but this is what happens in life and
this is what we want to say life in
action is very different from what we
tried to do and this is the story of the
music which I was playing just before
when we started is from in 1975 album by
an artist called Keith Jarrett now what
is so what is the backstory behind this
album the backstory behind this album is
in those days artists used to go from
town to town to perform in concert so
Keith was supposed to perform in :
for a show which was a sold-out show and
he was playing piano it was on a Sunday
when he reached call on the city his
host was a 17 year old girl and she
showed him it was pouring that day so
she showed him the piano and the
auditorium where he was supposed to play
when he saw the piano he freaked out he
freaked out because the piano was broken
and it was not the piano which he used
to play in concert he was driving
non-stop he was sleep-deprived and he
was presented a broken piano he said
that he cannot play this and he said you
just call up the big concert I will not
blame this I this can't happen the girl
pleaded with him that she will try to
reorganize a replacement but he should
not cancel the show he agreed and he
said ok the show was at 9:00 p.m. he
went to a restaurant dinner and
as it was a bad day from the beginning
he was the last person who got served on
that day at a restaurant so he came back
that girl could not organise a
replacement piano the concert hall was
full and he was asked to play a broken
piano and the music that we heard he's a
single largest selling piano jazz album
or a piano concert album since 1975 he
played the music and he just avoided not
name on the part where it was broken and
he created a music which is us which is
still considered as well as one of the
best single piano album which got
created
now why are we giving this two example
is because somewhere in ours our
struggle to only talk about success we
don't talk about the adversity which
comes before the success and adversity
and success have a very symbiotic
relationship they are not far from each
other they're they're very adjacent to
each other and if you do not tell our
children that the circumstances that
they will encounter in life are not
going to be the pleasant circumstances
they're gonna be difficult circumstances
sometimes heartbreaking circumstances
they will not be able to put this in a
in a in a perspective
now this come to this um I don't want to
do the textbook definition but this is
important because it has a three
components which I would like all at
their parents to see which are we have
highlighted in red then life skills are
adaptive they're necessarily positive
and they empower you
adaptive means you can you can change
them from different life stages they are
positive because they introduce a
positive element to in your action and
they empower you to do something then
they is not they will paralyze you but
they will empower you to do something
and that's why we need to work on
instilling life skills for our self in
our own behavior and then in our
children's behavior now these are the
what we have done we have combined all
the life skills from different areas
into five buckets but these five buckets
are it will spend some time in going
over their problem solving communication
thinking out of box and resilience so
these are the five buckets we will talk
about
now let's go one by one the first
version of area we want to talk about is
problem solving now it is easy that we'd
all understand its simplistic way water
problem problem solving is there is a
one definitive answer all our kids go to
school they learn maths if there is a
quadratic equation you solve a quadratic
equation you get a definitive answer you
solve a linear equation you will get a
different definitive answer now all
children need to learn some bit of
problem-solving in a structured manner
and stunning max provide added
structured way of thinking nowadays we
see many young women come as a global
problem right now right now they say
that they don't want to study maths so
what we would like to invite all parents
to see max not as a carrier direction
but see math as a life skill because it
is impossible it's like you cannot go on
with your life you should do not have
communication skill similarly the world
in which we are going our children will
have a huge difficulty if they do not
realize or they do not understand that
they have to solve maths problem so we
are not specifically focused on maths
problem what we would like you to think
and specially in a in a time like this
so a playing chess is easy is a kind of
a problem-solving playing crossword is
an is a is a problem-solving playing
pseudocode is a problem-solving why
don't we turn off the GPS on our mobile
phone and when you take out the car ask
your child to help you navigating to the
market to the whole that is a problem
solving so inviting children in day to
day activities and helping them who's
helped you solve the problem is a
problem solving now there is a recent
video which must have got circulated and
lots of whatsapp group where you would
have seen a robot arm making an omelet
so the two options you can make a an
omelet or you can make a sunny-side
now it is so interesting to see an
inanimate object just said I'm making an
omelet now all we all want our children
to learn robotics or coding and other
stuff now if anyone of you are
interested in seeing this video we can
circulate it later but what we would
like you to invite and think of this not
as a great robotics piece which it is
but what is it required to break down a
problem or a soulish or peaking of an
omelet in two simple steps and that is
also coding coding is not only that you
write as something in a particular
syntax so what this company did making
of an omelet was broken down into tasks
by task by task and then the Machine can
come and help you in doing that task we
in our at our home can invite children
to take any tasks starting from mopping
the floor to making a doll it can be
broken down into small steps and help
them get involved into that the day to
day activity and see them in
understanding that problems are not
confined to textbooks the problems are
there in the real life and they can help
in finding a solution the second aspect
we would like to invite you to think in
terms of life skill is a teamwork
now in some strange ways what we see all
around us we are becoming very
individualistic society now
individualistic I mean we want our kids
to do well in the class and in I some
phase we've got this idea that our kids
should not share the homework should not
share their plans and they should excel
in their own way the word in which we
are going is going to work on
collaboration people from different a
you would have seen one very corporate
buzzword is the diversity this bring a
diverse team in order why do you need a
diverse team because the problems are
becoming more and more ambiguous even
you take a problem like who build there
are 51 labs in the world from different
culture different socio-economic
societies are working round the clock to
solve that problem they can only solve
the problem if they openly share
whatever the steps and progress they are
making so that when the genome be this
is a one situation where the genome of
the virus was tracked in the record time
and when the genome was tracked it was
shared with everybody in the in the word
that this is the genome of the virus and
let's build a vaccine for for this so
this is the world we are getting into
and we invite parents to seriously think
about it how can we do I'd get the
children to work in t if you have two
kids at home and and you can you can
take it you can call yourself lucky
because it's it's good to have two kids
at home why don't you give them a task
which both of them have to do it
together
or you bring in a neighbor scared or
some other friends and give them a task
and the necessary part of the task is
both of them have to give to give some
part to each other to win that way if
they don't participate and if they don't
share it they cannot win it and that is
the inculcation we want early on to
happen at home
and that's why if and we will keep
talking about sports in in almost all
life skills
there's our team sports soccer and other
sports like hockey mouths water polo
these are the sports which the inculcate
that you need to take individual as a
backseat but help team win so we really
would like parents to think about it it
is a necessary skill for the next decade
and if you are only worried about your
child's progress
you're not helping them to prepare for
them for the world which they are
getting it now the third part we want to
talk about is communication now what we
see communication is very easily
understood but we would like to bring
four aspects of communication to you
four aspect of communications are
reading writing speaking and the fourth
one which doesn't get talked about is
listening so what has happening because
of the hyper connected word and this is
the other difference period generation
or the kids generation has that the kids
today don't know about a word where
mobile phone was not there in our life
mobile phone game but be if you have a
child any child was born after 2000 is
not aware of the world in which there is
no mobile phone now if that is a
situation what we see if reading all
around losing its charm now what we
would like you to bring at home both
books paper books not the Kindle variety
or not you read mystical on mobile
devices you would like you to invite
your children to read books if there is
a let's say 50 page book if they read 5
page every day in 10 days they can
finish a book so the so they learn in a
simple act like this they learn that a
task can be broken down into small
components and when you complete the
entire task you finish the book
so a book of fifty page or a hundred
page or 300 page may look unsurmountable
that oh I'm gonna be bored to my death
and reading this book but you should
break it into a small chunk it becomes
easily doable so reading we would like
barrel soup get it back because it's an
essential skill now why reading is an
essential skill because then you read
there is a there's an evocative imagery
of the birds gets created in your head
even if you've never stepped on to East
Africa and you've never been to savanna
grassland when you read about savanna
grassland the image of the savanna
grassland and mori tribe Mara tribe gets
created in your head so that's a deal in
white we seriously in fact in most of
our work you will see their little unded
it'll in our approach when we invite
parents to to do things we don't believe
in talking about create coding programs
or robotics or RT in artificial
intelligence and all that because they
they work on the foundation of solid
skills now the solid steel here is easy
he's inculcating some creativity in
thinking and that's why you need to
bring reading back to fashion at home
the second part we are talking about is
writing we work with the high school
students also and he's seen us a child
who's an a-star student if you ask them
to write 400 words they struggle
big-time the struggle big time because
they don't know how to write 400 words
and they see everything essay as an exam
and every write in a confined boundaries
the companies like Amazon I'm not so
sure how many of you are aware have
killed these slide presentation from the
company for any meeting in a company
like Amazon you need to write a
three-page note and circulate it before
the meeting and everybody who comes to
making has to have read the note and
then the weekend commences
so at Jeff Bezos don't we
he's a billionaire the world's richest
man but he's been writing to his
shareholders from the data company
started so there is a and for every year
there is a letter to shareholders which
Jeff has written so what we see is that
rewriting helps you distill in your mind
and and clear in your head the third
part speaking we think all parents are
very familiar with it they wanted kids
to participate in drama or theater and
everything so speaking is okay it is
well understood in our society and last
but not the least which we would night
parents to think about is listening now
listening is not a passive activity
listening is an active active engagement
with be with the person you are speaking
with or communicating with now for that
to happen
parents need to listen to the children
first and when they listen to the
children then the child will get a sense
that I've been understood and their
communication is not of the same level
as a parent so you to show lot of
patience in understanding things from
their perspective
and so what we will keep talking about
is the children imitate parents if the
end of overtime you are stressed out why
your children will not be stressed out
because they're watching you 24 by 7 if
you were having problem in dealing with
blurring of office and home your
children are having a problem in dealing
the blurring of school and pool so the
children's by sheer osmosis
they are watching your action every
single day and that's what parenting can
be very hard that you're constantly
under supervision of your children and
then noticing every small intonation in
your voice then see when you are getting
upset and that affects their mood and
their their their performance so the
communication part is something which we
want parents will listen and then
listening what we put it in the last we
would like to bring it to the top of the
communication scale that listening is
the first activity or communication
scale we should do it ourselves to
demonstrate to children
and the forth life scale which are
thinking out of the box if you
deliberately remove the world creativity
and you have three phases of thinking
out of the box now while you're doing
that because creativity is largely
interpreted as a fine art music painting
design something which is easier to rate
which is something god-gifted thing if
you have it you have it you don't have
it you don't have it it's the way we
process the you tivity while it's not
true all of us have creative elements
and we can hone it and we can make it
smarter and better for our own good and
for everybody around us what we have
rephrase it and coding it thinking out
of the box that every problem can have
multiple solutions
so now let's correlate the first one
which you talked about problem solving
and thinking out of the box problem
solving has a necessary component of a
definitive answer but it is leading to a
definitive answer when thinking out of
the box has multiple answer every
problem can have ten or fifteen
different solutions or different way of
solving it in fact one of the things you
can do at home pick up any object with
you and and tell your child tell us what
are the different ways it can be used so
they will learn to open their world and
see that there are different uses for
occur even if you're a paperweight at
home or anything from a flower mask to
anything you can let your imagination
run wild then the last part which we
want to talk about is resilience now how
do you inculcate resilience and it is
also seen as a kind of a personality
trait either you are resilient or you
are not resilient and if you see in we
are all of us in India now are in some
form of nocturnal or for more than three
months now so what is the three month
done to us at a emotional or
subconscious level there is an element
of loss the loss of freedom loss of
movement loss of bring out this loss
permeates all things
that we do today so it is an unnatural
world real living because this is an
unnatural word that you are giving in
every single day we are called upon to
demonstrate resilience to overcome what
has gone right or not acted that this
resilience is not taught in any school
it is a life skill that is required and
we will see more such episode almost
there is a study which came out or which
is saying it's quite possible that every
decade will see some crisis or the other
in 21st century if that is the landscape
that we are going ahead to then how do
we deal with resilience and one of the
best example of teaching resilience is
sports now I'm a big big fan of sports
for what a few very basic thing because
it teaches temperament the temperament
is that you will have a good day and you
will have a bad day but whether you have
a good day you won the match or you lost
the match next year you have to come for
the practice so what it teaches is that
it teaches a certain amount of
equanimity so when you see if you're
playing a cricket or you're playing a
tennis or you're playing badminton you
may lose a point where you give your
heart and soul but you have no other
option but in next few minutes you have
to face your opponent starts from all
over at home in a very simplistic way
that's what life is you had a good day
or a bad day but there is going to be
another day and you have to teach
through the good day also in the same
manner and you teach bad day you don't
have to wait till you become thirty year
old or forty year old or your midlife
crisis hits you and you can start
downloading meditation a band and start
thinking about it oh mindfulness I only
to get into some kind of a mindfulness
and all that that kind of mindfulness is
there in sports every single day and
every single book and the other aspect
of sports is it requires hard work over
a very sustained period of time if you
even if you are playing school
basketball a school level badminton or
table tennis or you're playing for your
house in the schoolhouse it will require
you to do some practice over a sustained
period of time and in doing that period
activities is over a sustained period of
time you will learn that success is
douchery it will come after I put in
Lord of harder hard work so this is
relentlessness of life you will learn
from from sports and the other aspect of
the all sports activities are fun and
there's so much of collateral benefit of
sports if you play sports you are active
I went to a school recently where the
the principal was from UK it was a very
prestigious school they invited
principal from abroad who had a huge
body of knowledge and he was explaining
his frustration then the 10th class
exams came and the school had a minimum
one hour of physical activity time
before the school started when the 10th
exams were supposed to come a month
prior to that the school came under so
much of pressure from parents that they
asked will to cancel the physical
activity class because the children need
to focus on studies and this principle
with 30 years of academic knowledge and
running schools behind schools was
totally at a loss he said what's wrong
with you or your society if you are
studying then sports will only make you
better at study because your your body
will function better you will sleep well
that half an hour 45 minutes one hour
you're spending sports you are not
distracted by mobile you will learn to
focus then he said I just can't stop
telling you benefit of sports but I see
parents withdrawing the children from
sports because their exams are coming so
they're two unrelated activity I'm sure
some of you will have some questions
then we'll talk about it but if we want
to build resilience there is a more than
enough documentary study the sports
the best way to go about it
all our children especially in
adolescent age will come under peer
pressure and one of the thing which we
use in the in the in the in the last
webinar when we talked about a study
from MIT on five principles of parenting
we invited parents who think from
parenting from five different angle not
from one and one of the key example of
that I keep talking about is that in our
society the other thing we do not teach
children is is money if said he's a
boo-boo subject it's a taboo subject
that that we don't teach children and
most children learn about money only
when they start working or becoming
independent I think it as a parents who
can help a great deal if you bring the
money conversation and the dining table
and at home and talk about it what is
the relative cost of their school
education the money that you make that
the amount of money which a car costs or
the petrol prices let the money is not
something which is a it's a textbook
subject or which is out in some outside
world it happens it is a part of our
daily life and you can help them in
overtime also then why don't you go and
buy vegetables but they will go and buy
vegetables and you give their money to
manage they will learn the relative
pricing of each each vegetable and they
will know that they can do the
transaction and they can do maths also
on the earn on their own so did this it
did not just longitudinal study done on
human happiness talks about building
healthy relationship if your child will
be on this planet for the next 60 70
years the single biggest reason what
will cause in happiness is the
relationship he or she is able to build
and modeling your relationship building
is not the way they see parents building
relationship so we would like parents to
think about it that they have to
inculcate the idea of there is something
called healthy relationship and there
are relationship
which are dysfunctional or which don't
have an only Bri Bri brings a negativity
so how to make a distinction between a
healthy relationship and dysfunctional
relationship paracin to bring this
subject out and talk about it
now these are the good things to have
communication scale problems always can
scale resilience but how do you tell
them how do how do you how do you build
it now the number one example is
emulating others and the number one role
models with children will follow are at
home parents so it is almost parenting
is almost like you are in spotlight
every single day it is very stressful I
know and we'll talk about it what
parents can do to distress themselves
when parenting is okay let me just put
it a very simple simple manner you
children not not listening to you but
they are copying you they do what you do
they don't listen to you okay so that's
a way so if they find there's a
disconnect between in what you are
saying and what they do they will follow
what you do not what you're saying so if
in some simple ways that the other thing
also is the burden who are the people
the family discusses on the dinner table
who are the role models you are bringing
out in the open that who are the people
the family admires or the parents like
or dislike the children will form some
reference point on that now the second
point we you turn to talk about is
mental conditioning mental conditioning
I'm sorry I think there is conditioning
spelling is wrong yeah the mental
conditioning is about taking a good day
and a bad day and the same stride they
need to see so I think this three and a
half months of lockdown is very
stressful for all of us they will see
what are the parents doing to cope with
it and they will learn about the mental
conditioning or emotional resilience
from parents and will fall copy that and
problem-solving we have already touched
upon it I would not talk about more
about this and the last part I have we
talked enough about sports the other
part which I want to bring now is the
music music is the best antidote to
sadness or lifting our woods or
depression known to mankind the one area
we talk all the time to parents that use
every armor in your skills to put your
children in that is to engage them in
music and sports and if you can start
doing that things along with their
betray vehicle so if you are if you
start playing a sport your children will
also start playing something or there
they may not play if you are playing
badminton they may not play badminton
they will do something else but they
will do it so please don't just teach
about music and sports without usual
still not being involved in it so a
great idea if you are involved with it
and then you bring them on and say let's
do it together and then the last part
which you talked about and it's very
relevant for the for the Cova ties that
we are in framing matters so there is
one very large study happened at Yale
University where a group of students was
exposed to a constant message the stress
is debilitating so their physical
parameters were taken before a two-week
knock study and the physical Parham and
interest two weeks the message which was
given to them
that stress is debilitating the other
group was was exposed to the message the
stress can get best out of you in all
they were told about the success story
they were talk of a told about the
adversity they were told about stories
when people were under extreme stress
but they could organize themselves
organize a team organized solution and
it got the best out of out of that since
the same message but what was what just
framing was different and after two
weeks and they measure the physical
response or physical attributes of the
to group by just tending the group the
stress is enhancing that group perform
exceptionally well on all parameter
what does it mean that it depends on us
whether we see something as constrained
or something as an opportunity to grow
so do we see three three and a half
months of knock down or overtime fit
2020 is gonna be a washout here or it is
going to be a liberating year where I
will discover something about myself I
will form new bonds in my family I will
reach out to my my loved ones and I will
restart and recalibrate my relationships
and everything it depends on us how do
we want to frame the Cova time had trust
us that our mind is very valuable the
message that we give our mind starts
following that
but this is what we talked about the
parents archetype behavior is most
important this is what we do you can go
and check out us on educator calm you
can leave a message contact us and
similar now we can talk about what
questions are what points do you have I
mean you have answered all my questions
and more no really you know for me life
skills was such a limited zone to me I
thought I was doing a great job because
I was teaching my child how to wash his
own toys and you know hang his own
clothes and in my head
those were life skills right and you
just broaden this horizon for me this is
so much more so thank you for that
because I mean it's it's like I said
it's really actually something I'm gonna
internalize because as you said it all
starts with us and we are those role
models you know and I keep reminding
myself of that over and over again that
it's so easy to complain about the child
and the child's behavior but we never
really internalize and look at what
we're doing just oh okay you've given me
a lot to think about I need to I need to
hold my own life skills now this is true
for all of us actually it's true for me
if super it requires day-to-day work
it's not something you just acquire it
and just keep it in safe it's a degree
which is you have earned and life with
the school zone after that no but even
even talking about sport you know the
way you spoke about it it all suddenly
started making so much sense that as a
child how I would get so you know I was
the sports captain of my school and I
used to get so demotivated on the days I
used to lose but I used to know that I
have to go back I have to go back I
can't give up and I didn't look at it as
a life skill all these years but now
that you've brought it to my notice
I know that that has played a very
important role in my life you know so
thank you thank you that was extremely
enlightening that was amazing okay
firstly before I ask my questions if any
of you have any questions please start
sending them
and we're gonna try and answer as many
of your questions as we can okay so
here's my question how soon should we
start inculcating these life skills 1 &
2 if we do start if you do say that
start from the earliest age then what
are those life skills that you would
teach a child between the age of say 1
to 5 ok so let's rewind this and this
this this answer little differently okay
I think somewhere once you become parent
it's a huge transition point in our life
I think the two three significant
transition points are when we become
economically independent is a transition
point in our life when we get into a
long-term relationship and get married
in this in a social sense it's a
transition point in our life and the
third significant transition point in
our life is when we have kids I think
you can't be little bit of business and
I don't care two hoots about life didn't
have kids I think all of us suddenly had
a responsibility being something else
when we become parents can you hold your
girl infant in your arm suddenly I
remember I became suddenly fearful of
time because suddenly I had had
responsibilities of a child with me I
think at that time recalibrate your life
and see what are the things you do bill
or you don't go back so I think what
we've been saying is that start from
yourself okay all of us have some areas
which you don't do well like suppose I
don't handle stress very well now what
can I do now become a parent I'm just
saying that you should not do earlier
but I'm saying at some stage you're to
start when you become a parent you may
ask yourself I don't deal with stress
very well now what should I do to deal
with stress very well can I take her
music as a as a G stressor and that
exports as at least Reserve can I do
meditation as a key stressor so you
learn to bring yourself in
or calibrated so norm or potential and I
think it children will learn from that
all parenting is about that you will be
a day when you will not be around and
your kids need to carry on with the life
so I think at some stage watching from
early on and yesterday with you and I
were talking about it the delayed
gratification children see very early
our children two years old can
demonstrate that they can pull their
impulse and they can do some self-talk
so this marshmallow test has been
administered all over the world to
children under the age of five I am the
- today at home I love you - video so
the very simple you can keep some
chocolate at home and tell your child
not to eat because you're going out for
two minutes and you back and then you
will share the chocolate with
interesting I'm gonna definitely try
this yeah and uh you see the children
are able to hold back themselves or not
able to hold back that sense that all
that and that that's the time you did
you have I think parents bigger role is
to keep observing the children and see
what they're doing well and what is that
they're not doing well and then nudging
their own response to it it will do so I
think a problem-solving everything the
five things that we talked about music
can start very early on you create a
child to you become sensitive their ears
to become sensitive to music it's a it's
a it's a life skill you can get your
child into swimming one in one and a
half-year-old
two years what kids can get into a pool
and learn swimming and all that I don't
think you need to teach them don't give
them a digital device that now you solve
candy crush or or do something please
don't do this with them at a very early
earlier I can tell you what not to do
that don't get if the digital device as
long as possible and all that but
otherwise involved I mean anything from
helping them to make a bread with you he
says also this was a life skill so so
the five dimensions that we
sher problem solving communication you
speak clearly to your child your child
is equally do you listen to your child
your child would listen to you so this
is communication problem solving
involving them in day-to-day activity
okay um why don't you go and put the
newspaper in the rack these isn't either
problem solving it similarly about now
the communication we talked about and it
won't be the meaning you think
day-to-day activity sometimes I worry
the peddles think that they need to
think special activity for the children
that the play time is something else and
we have literally play means play which
doesn't mean anything but everything
which happens in our house our playful
thing so it's our own attitude making
food isn't is one of the biggest
creative exercise or creative activity
known to all of us so so why don't we
involve children in making food as early
as possible
okay I don't want to put it into
brackets I think they don't in
everything that you do yeah
so you know again again once again it
all comes back to us and ourselves
because if we have that time we are
gonna inculcate that not kids but if we
are busy on our phones or our computers
we're going to say here's the iPad do
what you want you know so yep I guess it
always comes back to the parent
themselves it's very it's very stressful
when you decide you to become a parent
you signed on the dotted line I know
that I will be a barrier for the rest of
my life but absolutely absolutely yeah
okay I'm gonna ask you a question so how
do you deal with stress as a parent
during koban while you're while you're
seeing all of this and at the same time
ensure that one your child isn't getting
as you said right your child will absorb
that from you so how do you control that
stressful environment whatever may be
happening in your own life and not allow
it to enter your child right hmm that
obviously means that what you said is we
have to come back to mindfulness
ourselves and you know all of that I'm
assuming or how would we be able to
inculcate those life skills in ourselves
okay so so I think the first step is to
recognize the fact that is hard it's
hard for everybody if you have a parent
at home is hard for them if it's hard
for yourself because the boundaries
between office and home have got loud it
has to own a huge amount of uncertainty
around us as human beings the number one
thing which we don't like is uncertainty
yeah okay we do like uncertainty if I
step out of the home I want to know in
half an hour I will reach my destination
okay if suddenly that that simple point
is taken away from me that I don't know
whether I will reach in one hour or
five hours or three days it can cause
huge huge stress and among us so
suddenly all around us we see
uncertainity
a looming large so what we have to
realize is that this is not the time to
make some grand plan
so in fact 2020 is it is a year which
you need to break it down into smaller
chunks and say let's do only this much
okay let's not make something something
grand because you will not be able to
make it you will face you have to devise
it multiple times it is true for the
workspace also is true for for our life
is so I think that's that's the single
biggest important is to continue
continue your word and say these are the
only things we will do this year one the
second thing is you need to make some
form of activity calendar for yourself
okay which means that you depending on
whether you have a help at home or not
these are the things I will do at home
to help my spouse these are things I
will take care of it and I'm setting
aside half an hour an hour for myself to
be stressed I think what all of us need
to do that it is not an easy time and I
always give an example of traveling in
an aircraft and they were very not was
announcement happens by the air hostess
when you sit in the aircraft as a
security and safety drill that if the
decompression happens under the oxygen
masks will drop first you put the oxygen
mask on yourself even if even if you're
traveling with an infant or an elderly
person now this anak was information has
a huge truth in it yes you cannot take
care of your infant and your elderly
mother or father if you cannot take care
of yourself yes so if you world a
destress environment at home first you
need to de-stress yourself which means
you to actively take out that this half
an hour either I will do meditation I
will do reading I will listen to music
I would like suddenly I've discovered
doing dishes makes me distress so I play
music I play a music and I've been doing
now for almost every single day so it
distresses me it helps me unwind it and
I think I'm very good in that the way I
do it is I think I think I'm yeah but to
take pleasure in doing simple thing and
again it can be very gross you see the
other way but at the same time I think
the way I organize everything I do I
clean up the same the way I just
organize everything after that so hugely
I've just turned it upside down and I
play the music in the background that
about takes about a morning and evening
about half an hour forty minutes but
it's my time it's my time to do it I do
some bit of physical activity and some
bit of meditation I think you do carve
some space out for ourselves
and when we carve some space out for
ourselves the message that we are giving
to everybody around us in our family
that we need to actively work on
distressing it is not gonna happen
automatically nothing is gonna suddenly
go away this uncertainty is not going
away so to deal with the sunset
uncertainty we need to do few things
which we do very well and I do that
really well
got it got it
awesome I the line of you know use the
oxygen mask on yourself first before you
use it on others is officially my
favorite line I use it all the time
because I totally do believe in that if
I'm not a happy mother my child's not
going to be happy so and so it's so
important to work on self before we try
and work on others okay we've got a ton
of questions coming in so I'm gonna move
away from my questions now and ask you
these
we've got Anita asking us
my daughter is behaving very rude she's
only eight years old she loses her
interest in study every day her behavior
is getting worse me sorry me
and my wife are both working in school
as music faculty please guide us how we
can handle our daughter we lose her
faith
day by day she feels that we do not love
her what should we do for that - the
three four elements in this question
said this dissect them into one by one
the first part is the kid is behaving in
a rude manner now what we see and we
take an analogy open you go to a doctor
and you say suppose I have a migraine or
I have a body or some part is not
working with the doctor first the doctor
tries to build his in hypothesis then
why's that the doctor is not curing
immediately unless until is if it's a
serious issue is to understand the
things around it so what you see
rudeness is just a symptom of something
else okay so as a parent of a job is to
is to uncover that part be behind that
symptom what is their cause which is
making her hood look couple of things
you must understand or I think all of us
need to understand is that this block
town has children have not been able to
make sense of it and whatever things
which you've previously talking about
how do we distance ourselves please
don't talk about deaths and number of
infected people every day I think this
is the biggest disservice has been done
by all news organization that there is a
every user against - does it occur
running the number of affected people
number of dead people as if by counting
the makers feel feel feel easier you can
run once in the morning and evening it
will still give you the same information
that now that so one this constant
barrage of negative news doesn't help
anybody to tell you can you curtail the
information flow in it's not I'm not
asking you to per your head in the sand
I'm just asking you to for your own
sanity you need to channelize the
information now when coming to the kid
please see what is happening behind it
what is the cause and what is it getting
her emotional landscape disturb
the other thing what we have seen and
this that has come out from the studied
which has been done in Spain on the
children there the lack of motivation
because suddenly see we are all over the
30 plus 35 40 plus and all that we can
still make some sense of it now try to
see yourself in an eight-year-old
position suddenly every activity which
is supposed to be normal activities is
not allowed and they don't know how to
make sense of it and because they don't
know how to make sense of it the the
response is coming in different ways
some children are becoming very clingy
to their parents some children are
becoming very aloof some children are
becoming very irritable and the lack of
motivation is all around so what they
need is some time from you aware and
sometimes people ask parents ask it's a
quality time or a quantity time
I wish their easy answer then we both
they need both quality or the quantity
please spend some time with them and
just listening to the immense as
observing them they're known to be an
agenda that okay tell me what's going
wrong with you children never answer
that if it doesn't tell me is something
good I listen to them physically hurt
they will not share and this is we're
talking about emotional landscape so
just shows a little bit of more patience
and love and remember she just eight
years old eight years is eight years we
have to go down to her level to
understand that what is her world and
what is causing that in fact in the
previous webinar we used a line which is
very cool emotionality is not fragility
and I think it is stuck in my head if
our children are behaving emotionally
upset behavior it's not there they're
there scarred for life or that the life
is going to be totally different thing
it is a tough time and there will be
some bad days so let's take the bad days
at the bad tale it's not that that it
has affected them insignificant thank
you thank you I'm sure that that's
answered their question okay we're going
to move on to the next question from the
audience someone is seeing one of my
grandson's
hypersensitive and sometimes
uncomfortable how do I control him are
there any activities to control okay so
the word control
I don't like especially controlling
children yeah they're destructive and
that throwing things around and all that
so even in there's tweaking surrounds
you did you've seen all of us have been
to a mall when the children sprawl down
on the floor and they're too intent
rooms and all other things and all that
if you just step back and similar to
what the previous question was the step
back and all that is a cry for help or
the cry that I have not been understood
so I think what the parents are the
grandparents are supposed to do is to go
behind the observed behavior and in some
sense it is it is a hard work which
parents or grandparents or or auntie or
uncle need to demonstrate that what is
causing that it is not that we are not
trying to control the demonstrative
behavior I think if you want to manage
it you understand what is the reason
behind that irritation why are they
suddenly or it is happening for some
time the word is very very different
from our world and I can't impress upon
enough that that their age is their age
they are we should not process it from
our age we should put an adult filter
but if you want to understand their of
mood and what is upsetting them we need
to go and think it from or understand
what is happening and then sometimes you
need to give a clear unambiguous message
now clear unambiguous message and if you
allow me that we take an example of
faith and what are the some time a
simple message it can go wrong my
friends bar child is in 10th standard in
the mid middle of March before the log
don't happen he was in board exam and
his birthday wasn't in
in the beginning of March so the parents
were very concerned because this kid was
very fond of cake so they got a cake at
home and they told him just eat a small
portion and don't eat the whole cake
because once your exams are over with
throw a party for you and then you can
eat as much cake as possible as you like
Wendy came back after half an hour an
hour that kid polish of the entire key
parents were distraught that we told him
not to eat what happens if he falls sick
then in the middle of the exam what are
we gonna do and at all the baby the
thing which a distraught parents can
can't go through doctors thing from a
child's perspective
first of all just pause and think about
it what what happened here and all that
he said he's the building man but it's
it's over a 10th grade students will be
what 14 15 year old he's not eating the
entire cake is not okay today it is not
okay after 15 days it is not okay after
15 months also yeah so so how do you
reconcile it is your messaging ISM is
wrong a messaging is wrong you're saying
after 15 days you can eat as much as you
like but don't eat eat today
so so the best thing is that you you
should not eat now
or you should not need later also there
is a small portion there's something you
need to share with everybody else so the
basis is some time as a parents because
we know that there is a exam time there
is something bill the discontinuity we
can process information five different
ways but the children don't process
information in that place so I I
sincerely request all parents to go
behind and think of themselves as a
doctor the first job is investigation
the doctor doesn't prescribe medication
medication immediately the doctor does a
test investigation he takes blood
pressure it takes politics yeah your
your your your your your uses a
stethoscope if you still not got the
hang of it he'll send you to a path lab
let the now run some more tests to
simulate a body of information to arrive
at that what is happening so my request
to parents is to put on a Chan
hols had and do some investigation
around it don't look for solving what
you see in front of you
amazing amazing okay we've got a
question from pretty-pretty is asking
what kind of communication should be
used for a pre adolescent child around
nine to eleven especially when they are
not able to manage their angle see there
are two parts I want to divide and some
questions are similar in nature is this
Koba time or pre Koba time or is a
continuous behavior another if you see
some things have changed in your
children the behavior and they would be
if you ask your spouse to notice few
things in your behavior in the Cova time
they would notice it we are very poor
judge of our own responses and he need
some time an outsider to give us an
honest feedback so if you ask your
spouse she or he or she will tell you
how is that Cova time has affected you
or or what change in your behavior it
has caused so similarly if your child
the behavior change you see is in over
times then you have to grant that
leniency or a certain latitude that
because we are in the unnatural
situation that response pertains to this
unnatural setting we are in okay so
because we are an unnatural setting then
a very emotional landscape is disturbed
in fact there are situations where the
children stress level and it could be
for multiple reasons
suppose I used to go to school and every
day else to talk to somebody who was
America my close friend suddenly for
weeks together there is no communication
with my friend and not being able to
talk to a friend is the calamity in
their age group yes but but we don't
know about that that thing at all that
they will not be able to come and talk
to us about and if our world is
constantly busy with zoom meeting office
saying and after thing
then they will suddenly see no space for
them to come and speak with you so you
need to carve out some space which are
family time I know it's difficult I'm I
admit is not easy for parents right now
but you need to make an extra effort and
recognize for your own mental well-being
that we are in our uncharted territory
if we are in our charter territory trust
me that our kids are in a very very
different different space so we need to
help them to cope with it and say the
other thing which we we didn't talk
about it parents are the authority
figure in their lives so what is the
message which parents are giving and one
of the message which should come out in
unambiguous manner for the children is
this is going to get over
okay you have to tell your kids in no
uncertain terms without giving any ifs
and buts which will be over and you will
go back to your school we will go on a
holiday we'll go out and eat we'll go
for a movie because they need to hear
that this is not gonna be permanent and
you believe it yourself yes believe it
yourself that it is a temporary
phenomena yes what your message you are
giving to your children as the tough
times don't last all the time yes so
there are good days and the bad days and
but tough times also comes with an
expiry date it will get over yes and you
ever tell them that this will be over
until however fun will do all the
activities which you were doing earlier
you know talking about that I have been
introspecting so much myself through the
lockdown and I think as a person I have
awakened and I have grown so much more
because I have to be more well patient
and tolerant right because again as you
said I am that role model for my child
so I feel like in this lockdown there's
so much we can do to be the best
versions of ourselves right before
trying to worry about everybody else so
yeah I'm gonna keep on that track and
we're gonna ask you the last question of
the day now this is from Ashish
she says my son is awaiting his tenth
grade results is CBSE results which is
likely on the 15th of July
what other things parents can do if
there are disappointments in terms of
results okay unfortunately and this is
what the work we do we see the pressure
which comes on children at the time of
tense exam and 12th exam is
disproportionate for their age you
handle we almost make them as
life-defining women if there's anything
I can say with certainty that no tenth
or twelfth or a college or a job or
anything is a life defining moment but
can me you cannot go out in your life
and say if I work for let's say Google
my life will be done if I work for
McKinsey my life will be done if I win
our lumpy gold medal my life will be
done no there is no such thing like that
oh if I marry such and such person my
life will be will be the best and all
that so similarly I think of Akeem it
starts from us to tell our children that
it is one more step in your life journey
it is not D step it is not these step
that everything else will be over and
out after that other so I think the
first message which needs to come to
your your tech and one of the parenting
pillar we talk about is parents need to
give another unambiguous message that I
have your back that I will support you
come what may be the result and you and
I can only manage our effort level and
that's the only thing that you do so
what I will tell the child that as long
as you're honest about your effort the
desert can be whatever it is and
whatever result comes you can build a
life on that yes okay so note that you
can only build on life only when it's 95
and 97 percent or when you get into
iit-bombay or when you get into such a
such Institute and all that he's not
life can be built at any stage from any
platform from whatever it perceive how
perceptually bad it look it can be built
anytime anywhere now there are other
things which happens so one this is a
message from the parents what we see at
all itself these these are highly
stressed highly stressed in Cove attire
but without Koba time took over time has
only accentuated it
why has they've they've been stressed
because there's a lot of peer pressure
if I'm in a group where four of my
friends are nerds or academically
superachiever
I have that much of pressure to do well
or if suddenly I don't want to be
singled out in the class as a student
who has not done well so the children
word is not only the word which there is
at home there the world which is outside
in the peer group which plays a huge
role on the emotional mental makeup so
as a parent our job is to know what is
that world what my child is getting
messages from that world does that word
make him feel big him or her feel
inferior
not good enough so one so not only
parents need to keep the message but if
the child is in a group he or she is
getting bullied but they are pointing
fingers at a.m. that see you could get
even this much of marks but we got so
much how I don't know so but I think
what is important for parents know what
is the peer group this child is
operating in and is he or she getting
some negative message from there so so
summarizing in two points the message
needs to I have I have your back and
whatever may be the result we can build
life on that and it can be exceptional
life it doesn't it doesn't need to end
exceptional life as X in finite
dimension it not only one being a
dimension to it and the second is we
will support you and observe the social
setting they are a amazing amazing I'm
sure that everyone who's heard you speak
to me is gonna take something back and
is gonna reflect into their own lives I
know I am because I think you know it's
so important like you said covert or no
covert it's so important for us as
parents to really reflect on our own
behavior and our own the causes we're
creating in a day on a daily basis
versus only looking externally to see
what is happening in our environment so
thank you thank you so very much
I share all this wonderful knowledge
with us thank you appreciate it
immensely and I'm sure everyone
listening has loved this episode of that
was brought to us by wellness 360 in
tune with ICICI Lombard and thank you
I'm sure
Harish Sharma has enlightened you all he
shared his details so anyone who was it
sorry
and yeah I know I am definitely going to
get in touch with you I know I'm gonna
get a lot of my friends to get in touch
with you because this is so important
it's so important for all of us to know
how to handle our children in today's
times so thank you thank you very much
it must thank you really appreciate it
thank you thank you very much thank you
yep 5-cc
you